还剩一个饺子  谁要吃
Uh, one dumpling left. Who wants it?
或许你该让给怀孕的那位女士
Maybe you should offer it to the pregnant lady.
那位女士是...
And that would be...
我啊  谢尔顿
Me, Sheldon.
我孕相多明显啊
I'm obviously pregnant.
因为你还没当面跟我说过
Well, you never said it to my face.
而我上一次想当然地认定一名女士怀孕时
And the last time I assumed a woman was pregnant,
结果还挺糟糕的
it did not go over well.
没错  我还在生你气呢
Yeah, I'm still mad at you.
你这酒鬼当时居然在喝白开水
You were drinking water instead of wine.
我这么想能怪我吗
What was I supposed to think?
谢尔顿说得对
Sheldon's right.
我永远不会问一个女士是不是怀孕
I would never ask a woman if she was pregnant,
除非是她告诉我  或是我看到有人类
unless she tells me or I see a human being
从她下面被拉出来
wiggling out of her.
谢尔顿  我怀孕了
Well, Sheldon, I'm pregnant.
恭喜你啊  怀孕多久了
Congratulations. How far along are you?
大概三个月吧
About three months.
才三个月吗
Only three?
天啊  你肚子里是装的是几胞胎啊
Good gravy, how many babies are in there?
够啦  咱们来聊一些
Okay, let's talk about something
不会让我的孕妻暴怒的话题吧
that won't infuriate my pregnant wife.
我读了一个有关大象的有趣知识
I read an interesting fact about elephants.
再换一个
Try again.
我想到啦
Oh, I've got something.
这周五我要接受电台访谈啦
I'm being interviewed on public radio this Friday.
厉害  为什么呢
Oh, cool. How come?
大学希望物理系能获得
Uh, the university is trying to get more funding
更多研究资金
for the physics department,
所以就派我出马啊
so they want me to go out and talk it up.
真的吗  派你啊
Really? You?
那他们还真是请对人了
Well, they picked the right person for the job.
真是谢谢啊
Thank you.
我觉得他信了
I think he bought it.
第十一季  第二集
知名电台主持人  曾在本剧第7季第10集客串过
欢迎收听《科学星期五》  我是艾拉·菲莱
Hi, I'm Ira Flatow, and this is Science Friday.
今天的嘉宾是物理学家莱纳德·霍夫斯塔德
Joining me today is my guest physicist, Dr. Leonard Hofstadter,
他要来跟我们聊他在加州理工
to talk about all of the exciting research
所做的那些激动人心的研究
they're doing at Cal Tech.
感谢贵节目给我这个机会...
Thank you for having me. Whoa...
还是没办法习惯在耳机里听到自己的声音
Could never get used to hearing myself in headphones.
我的声音听起来真是这样吗
Is that really how I sound?
是的  真是
It is. It is.
很高兴知道这点
That is good to know.
我跟他说过他的声音很惹人厌
I told him his voice was annoying.
他就是不听
He didn't want to listen.
喂
Hey.
难道你觉得不烦人吗
You're saying it's not?
就...
Just...
喂...
hey.
所以打从五年前
So, it has been five years
希格斯玻色子被证实存在后
since the discovery of the Higgs boson--
您觉得下一个科学界大事是什么
what's the next big thing gonna be?
这很难说啊
Wow, that's hard to say.
有太多大事在发生了
There's so much going on.
我们一直在搜集大量的数据
We've been collecting tons of data
而这数据有可能颠覆我们对宇宙的理解
that could revolutionize the way we understand the universe.
比如说  有个粒子叫超对称性夸克
For instance, there's a particle called a squark,
它能证明超对称性
which could prove supersymmetry.
有意思  那你们找到了吗
That is interesting. Have you found it?
-什么  这个夸克吗  -对啊
- What, the squark? - Yes.
没  还没
No, no.
找到就是神作了
Wouldn't that be exciting?
但我们也在试着找出超电子
But we're also looking for the selectron,
都是理论物理学家提出的物理模型中假想的一些粒子
基本没有切实的实验依据  很可能并不存在
胶微子与超中微子
the gluino and the neutralino.
-那找到那些了吗  -没有
- Well, and have you found that? - No.
插个有趣小故事
Another fun sidenote--
我有个高中同学名叫特丽莎·胶微子
I went to high school with a girl named Theresa Gluino,
但要找到她并不需要花20亿
but it didn't cost $2 billion to find her.
她总躲在体育馆后面抽着烟
She was smoking behind the gym.
那你们发现了什么
So, what have you found?
其实什么都没发现
Uh, nothing, actually.
他可以说这话吗
Should he be saying that?
应该不可以
Uh, probably not.
对啊  这可是公共电台
Yeah, this is public radio.
难道他不知道"还有人"在听广播节目吗
Doesn't he realize that dozens of people might hear him?
但我还是很有信心
But I remain confident.
我们有最好的仪器与最顶尖的科研人员
We've got the best equipment and the best minds
一起在努力着呢
all working on it.
还好  感觉他把场救回来了
Okay, sounds like he's back on track.
虽然有时候我会觉得...
Although, some days I'm, like, ugh...
我们花了好多好多钱啊
we've spent so much money.
怎么屁都没找到  我们是在干嘛啊
Why haven't we found anything? What are we doing?
哎妈
Oh, boy.
莱纳德来了
There's Leonard.
估计他今天很不好过
I'll bet he's having a rough day.
我们尽量表达支持吧
Let's just try to be supportive.
支持他个鬼
Supportive?
他公开诋毁了我一生挚爱
He publicly maligned the love of my life,
物理女士
Lady Physics.
这挚爱最好别让你的未婚妻女士知道
You might not want to mention that to Lady Fiancee.
大家好
Hey, guys.
今天好吗
Hey, how's it going?
怎么  你有什么话想说吗
What? You got something to say?
我刚才已经说了啊
I think I just said it.
口不一
P-f-f.
呸
Pff!
我当时只是实话实说啊
Look, I-I was just speaking the truth.
我们是科学家  不应该用事实说话吗
We're scientists-- isn't that what we're supposed to do?
你懂个大西瓜的事实啊
Oh, what would you know about the truth?
你还觉得《星球大战I  魅影危机》很不错呢
You thought Phantom Menace was "Not half bad."
你怎么可以泄密
I told you that in confidence!
大家冷静  别吵架了
Okay, calm down. Everybody just cool it.
别拦着啊  要是我们运气好
No, let 'em go. If we get lucky,
说不定他们俩能有人吵哭呢
maybe one of them will start crying.
能不能不聊这个  像成年人一样地吃午饭
Uh, can we just drop this and have lunch like adults?
-行  -好吧
- Fine. - Very well.
-莱纳德  -怎么了
- Leonard? - What?
呸
Pff!
准备好去吃饭了吗
You ready for lunch?
马上就好
Oh, one second.
某人这里多了好多新的酷炫设备啊
Ooh, someone's got a lot of fancy new lab equipment.
对啊
I know.
大学给我的研究投了好多钱呢
The university has been throwing money at my study.
运气好的话
With any luck,
以后说不定能有脑疾病用我名字为名呢
there'll be a brain disease with my name on it.
两指交叉为你祈祷
Fingers crossed.
讽刺的是  如果你患上了福勒瘫
Which is ironic, because if you had Fowler's palsy,
你的手将无法两指交叉
you wouldn't be able to cross your fingers.
我很意外谢尔顿居然不来这里
I'm surprised Sheldon's not up here playing
玩你的新玩具
with all your new toys.
其实我还没告诉他呢
Actually, I haven't told him about it.
我们这边获得的经费比物理那边多太多
We've been getting so much more funding than physics,
他对此略为敏感
he's been a little sensitive.
所以你就对他隐瞒了你的成功吗
So you're just gonna hide your success from him?
我知道不好
I know.
-我是不是太坏了  -不会啊
- Am I terrible? - No.
我也这么做
I do that, too.
美国普通城市
不然他怎么会以为我的公司年会在博伊西
How he thought my company retreat was in Boise?
著名度假海岛
其实在塔希提岛
It was in Tahiti.
那我就松一口气了
That's such a relief.
我内心曾隐隐觉得这样对谢尔顿有失公允
I mean, part of me was worried I was being unfair to Sheldon.
将你的恻隐之心藏起来
Take that part of yourself and hide it away.
就像我藏起我去年
Just like I did with last year's bonus check
"并没发"的奖金支票
that I "didn't get."
戴维斯女士  你有事找我吗
Ms. Davis, you wanted to see me?
是的  霍夫斯塔德博士  快进来
Yes, Dr. Hofstadter, come on in.
我是该坐下还是站着
Should I sit or stand?
我没被召进过主任办公室  不懂规矩
I'm not used to being called into the dean's office.
请坐
Please, sit.
不得不说  还真是有点紧张啊
I have to say I'm a little nervous.
应该的
You should be.
我知道我搞砸了
Look, I know I screwed up,
但就是一次访谈而已
but it was only one interview.
能对学校造成多大的损害呢
How much damage could it have caused?
你想听我念念收到的邮件吗
Would you like for me to read you the e-mails
学校的捐助者们都在问如果物理是条死路
from donors asking why are they giving us money
那给咱们捐钱的意义何在
if physics is a dead end?
我可没说物理是条死路
I didn't say it was a dead end.
我只是说我担心可能会这样
I just said that I was worried it might be.
那如果我说我担心
So if I just said I was worried
你可能下周就要失业了
you might not have a job next week,
你感觉怎么样
how would you feel?
头晕  还好你让我先坐下
Light-headed, and glad you asked me to sit down.
好吧  你就说我该怎么做吧
Okay, just tell me what I can do.
我要你发表一份声明
I'm gonna need you to make a statement
说自己言论有失  并且你坚信
saying that you misspoke, and that you're confident
物理学界即将迎来一个重大突破
the physics community is close to a major breakthrough.
你想让我撒谎
You want me to lie.
听着  霍夫斯塔德博士  我就指望你了
Look, Dr. Hofstadter, I'm counting on you.
我认为你是本校最聪明的物理学家
I think that you are the smartest physicist at this university.
真的吗
Really?
瞧  撒谎一点都不难
See? Lies. They're not that hard.
感觉某人今天很用功啊
Looks like you've been busy.
是啊
Oh, I have.
暗物质  调和广义相对论与量子力学的矛盾
Uh, dark matter, uh, reconciling gravity and quantum mechanics.
超对称性
Supersymmetry.
我已经搞清了当今物理界最大的几个难题
I've figured out the biggest problems in physics today.
你都解出来了吗
Wow, you solved them all?
不  我只是清楚知道了它们是最大的难题
No, I just, I figured out that they're the biggest problems.
是因为莱纳德在电台上说的话吗
Is this about what Leonard said on the radio?
当然不是
Absolutely not.
我也不想谈论莱纳德
And I do not want to talk about Leonard.
我们能谈点别的事情吗
Can we please just talk about anything else?
我们可以谈谈我的一天
We could talk about my day.
我真是自己挖坑自己跳  对吧
Walked right into that one, didn't I?
既然你勉强算是问了
Well, since you sort of asked,
我今天其实过得非常开心
I actually had a very good day.
我的实验室多了不少新设备
Got some new equipment for my lab.
那恭喜你啊
Well, congratulations.
我也有新设备
I got some new equipment, too.
这些马克笔
I got these markers.
水果味的哦
They smell like fruit.
我买的时候完全没有注意到
Which I did not notice when I bought them.
我一点也不喜欢
Don't really care for it.
给  喝这个
Here, drink this.
或许会有帮助
It might help.
万一没有呢
What if it doesn't?
所以我给你拿来一整瓶呀
Well, that's why I brought the bottle.
走廊没有一个人愿意跟我说话
No one would talk to me in the halls.
大家都瞪着我
They just glared at me.
感觉就像又过了一遍高中生活
It's like high school all over again.
我超级想再过一遍高中生活
Oh, I would totally do high school all over again.
-但那对你没帮助  -没有
- But that doesn't help you. - No.
我被叫去了行政办公室
I got called in to the administration office.
瞧瞧我的坏小子  居然被校长叫过去
Ooh, look at my bad boy getting called to the principal.
严格来说  我们没有校长
We don't technically have a principal.
有个常务委员会在监督学校预算
There's a standing committee that oversees the budget.
瞧瞧我的坏小子
Ooh, look at my bad boy
回答没人问你的问题
answering questions nobody asked.
拜托  你不过是在电台说了几句傻话
Hey, come on, look, you said a few dumb things on the radio--
最坏又能怎样呢
what is the worst that could happen?
我可能会被解雇
I may get fired.
好吧  就算被解雇了  你也可以找别的工作啊
Okay, well, even if you did, you could find another job.
谁会想聘用一个在公开场合
Yeah, who wouldn't want to hire the physicist
说物理已死的物理学家
who publicly said physics is dead?
我不会把这项写在简历的"特殊技能"里
Well, I wouldn't put that under "Special skills."
我可以弥补
I can fix it,
我只需写一份违心的撤回声明即可
I just need to write a retraction I don't believe in--
基本就是出卖灵魂来保住饭碗
basically sell out to keep my job.
很好  那我不打扰你写稿子了
Great, I'll leave you to it.
谢尔顿  是我
Sheldon, it's me.
干嘛
What?
我知道你很生气  但我得写一份声明
Look, I know you're mad, but I have to write a statement
说物理学界即将迎来一个重大突破
that says the physics community is close to a breakthrough,
既然你是真的相信会这样
and since you actually believe that,
我非常需要你的帮助
I could really use your help.
抱歉  我做不到
Sorry, I can't.
拜托  别这样嘛
Come on, don't be like that.
我做不到是因为我觉得你是对的
I can't, because I think you were right.
什么
What?
听着
Look.
不是所有科学都能取得成功
Not all science pans out.
超对称性至今在自然界中尚未被观测到
数十年来  我们都希望超对称性是真的
You know, we've been hoping supersymmetry was true for decades,
终于我们制造出大型强子对撞机
and finally, we built the Large Hadron Collider,
本应该通过发现新粒子来证实该理论
which is supposed to prove it by finding these new particles,
然而并没有
and it-it hasn't.
或许超对称性
And maybe supersymmetry,
人类最后的大想法  其实是错误的
our last big idea, is simply wrong.
听起来真惨
Well, that sounds awful.
我懂为什么大家都讨厌我了
Now I get why everyone hates me.
但从好的方面来看
Well, on the bright side,
一起共事15年后
after working together for 15 years,
你终于能听到我说"你当时说得对"
you finally get to hear me say, "You were right."
是啊
Oh, yeah, you did.
感觉如何
How's it feel?
基于我可能会失去工作
Mm, given I might be unemployed,
苦乐参半吧
bittersweet.
-读给我听听  -稍等
- Read it back to me. - Oh, hang on.
"的确  也许有人会质疑我们
"Yes, one might question the $20 billion
在建造运行大型强子对撞机上耗费的200亿
to build and run the Large Hadron Collider,
但在另一方面..."
but on the other hand..."
行吧
Okay.
"在另一方面  与预测相违背的是
"On the other hand, contrary to predictions,
对撞机没有如我们所预测般创造出
the collider didn't create a small black hole
足以毁灭整个地球与生命的小黑洞
that devoured the Earth and life as we know it.
所以...
So, s--
这钱花得值啊"
money well spent."
太丧了
This is depressing.
你这儿有酒吗
Do you have any alcohol around here?
佩妮搬出去的时候  不出所料地
Uh, not surprisingly, when Penny moved out,
带走了每一滴酒
she took every last drop. Um...
不过我这儿有几瓶从漫展上买回来的
Oh, but I do have several bottles of Romulan ale
罗慕伦麦酒
that I bought at Comic-Con.
不就只是伏特加里加了蓝色素吗
Isn't that just vodka with blue dye in it?
先是物理  现在又是罗慕伦麦酒
First, physics, now Romulan ale.
你还想往哪些东西头上拉泡屎呢
What else would you like to defecate on?
我还以为你很快会回来
I thought you were coming right back.
本来是  但是我们都很郁闷
I was, but we're both depressed,
所以决定一醉方休
and decided to drown our sorrows.
喝漱口水吗
In mouthwash?
有些漱口水中含有酒精
让我想起了以前的夏令营时光
Man, that is so summer camp.
这是《星际迷航》里的罗慕伦麦酒
I-It's Romulan ale, from Star Trek.
帝国战争时期  罗慕伦麦酒
It was briefly legalized during the alliance
在罗慕伦帝国与星际联邦的结盟期间
between the Romulan Empire and the Federation
有过短暂的合法售卖
at the time of the Dominion War.
现在换我郁闷了
Aw, now I'm depressed.
我告诉他越多我实验室的事  他就越生气
The more I told him about my lab, the pissier he got.
你知道他跟我说了什么话吗
You know what he said to me?
他说  "我希望你实验的所有相关性
He said, "I hope all your correlations
都无法被证明"
turn out to be specious."
他当面对你说这话吗
He said that to your face?
真是个混蛋
What a dick.
你是个事业成功的女人
You know, you're a successful woman.
你有偶尔吹嘘下自己成就的权利
You should be able to brag about your accomplishments once in a while.
是啊  你也可以啊
Well, so should you.
他们就从来不会不敢吹嘘
I mean, the guys are never shy about bragging.
可不是嘛  每次华仔玩《魔兽争霸》
Tell me about it. Howie texts me
他的狗升级了都要发短信告诉我
every time his dog levels up in Warcraft.
他有打电话就为了告诉你
Has he ever called you to tell you
他在一个花生里发现了三颗花生仁吗
he found three peanuts in one shell?
谢尔顿就干过这种事
'Cause Sheldon has.
我们也应该可以这么做才对
We should be able to do that, too.
我们可以互相跟对方吹嘘啊
I guess we can brag to each other.
这个想法很不错
That's a great idea.
当然了  这可是老娘想出来的
Damn right it is; I came up with it.
感觉真爽
That felt good.
医药品行业的钱多得花不完
You know, there's so much money in pharmaceuticals,
我们从来不洗试管
we don't even wash out our test tubes.
直接扔了换新的
We just throw them out and get new ones.
我刚拿到了一台功能性磁共振成像仪
I just got a brand-new, state of the art fMRI machine.
这仪器超贵啊
Whoa. Those things are so expensive.
对啊
I know.
有时候我就躺进里面打个盹
Sometimes, I just lie down in there and take a nap.
就是张身价百万的单人床
It's like a million dollar bunk bed.
我上班时有两个助理
At the office, I have two assistants.
我都不知道他们的名字
I don't even know their names,
就叫他们一号和二号
I just call them Thing One and Thing Two.
真好  我没有助理
That's great. I-I don't have assistants.
这大概就是在私企的福利之一
Oh. I guess that's one of the benefits of being in the private sector.
有助理  钱还挣得多
That and all the money I make.
对  你赚大把[黑心卖药]钱
Yeah, you've got that.
而我有节操与一身正气
I've got my integrity.
要分优劣怕是会伤了你的自尊
Hard to say which is better without making you feel bad.
所以说  你们不开心
Okay. So you guys are upset
是因为对撞机反证了你们的理论吗
because the collider thing disproved your theories?
比这更糟
I-It's worse than that.
多年来对撞机上都没有任何发现
It hasn't found anything in years,
我们不知道我们的理论是对是错
so we don't know if we're right, we don't know if we're wrong.
不知道下一步该怎么办
We don't know where to go next.
我只知道我看起来像跟阿凡达舌吻过
All I know is it looks like I tongue-kissed Avatar.
别泄气
Come on.
你们是物理学家
You guys are physicists.
好吗  你们永远都是物理学家
Okay? You're always gonna be physicists.
的确  研究物理有时候很艰难
And sure, sometimes, the physics is hard,
可不就是艰难造就了它的无聊吗
but isn't that what makes it boring?
我们来了  什么情况
We're here. What's going on?
就我看来
Okay. As far as I can see,
科学已死
science is dead,
是莱纳德杀了它
'cause Leonard killed it.
还有
And, uh,
我不认识什么罗慕伦人
I don't know who the Romulans are,
但是他们可懂怎么寻欢作乐了
but those guys know how to party.
那你想要我们干什么
So, what do you want us to do?
我不知道  你们才是科学家  哄他们开心
I don't know. You're scientists; cheer them up.
"哄他们开心"
"Cheer them up"?
你到底知不知道科学家是干什么的
Do you even know what a scientist is?
不  我们不需要人哄
No, we don't need to be cheered up.
只是刚发现物理就跟《迷失》一样
It just turns out that physics is exactly like Lost.
著名科幻美剧  共6季  开播时广受好评  最后基本算烂尾
开篇极佳  追到结尾才发现就是在浪费生命
Started out great, and turns out just a big old waste of time.
狗屁  你知道你们听起来像什么吗
Boo-hoo. You know what you sound like?
像小娃娃
Babies.
两个哭哭啼啼的小娃娃
Two whiny babies.
世界上最惨的事就是被两个
And there's nothing worse than being stuck
哭哭啼啼的小娃娃给包围
with two whiny babies!
我的天啊  我之后就要有两个娃了
Oh, my God, I'm gonna have two babies.
别别别  小娃娃可棒了
No, no, no, no. Babies are great.
你有两个娃非常幸福啊
You're lucky to have two babies.
你看我  形单影只单身狗
I mean, look at me, uh, I'm all alone.
一辈子永远别想有娃
I'm never gonna have babies,
因为跟自己的狗一起网上看剧是无法生娃的
'cause you can't make a baby watching Netflix with your dog.
谢两位壮士到场支援
Thanks for coming.
我虽然赚的钱可能没你多
I may not make as much money as you,
但至少我知道我在做的工作
but at least I know that I'm actually doing something
能让人们生活更加美好
that makes people's lives better.
我的工作也能让人们生活更加美好啊
Hey, my work makes people's lives better.
尤其是当你患有中度到重度湿疹
Especially if you have moderate to severe eczema
且不介意掉几颗牙齿时
and don't mind if you lose teeth.
你说得对
You're right.
我们都从事重要的工作
We both do important work.
我试图绘制出大脑的结构
I'm trying to map the structures of the brain,
你试图说服人们
and you're trying to convince people
真有头发痒这件事
that itchy hair is a real thing.
的确真有其事
It is a real thing.
这碰巧是我们公司胆固醇药导致的副作用
It happens to be a side effect of our cholesterol drug.
我只是在说我的研究
I'm just saying that my research
可能真的会永远改变世界
may actually change the world forever.
但愿如此
I hope it does.
因为到时我会坐在一艘超大游艇上看这个世界
'Cause I'm gonna see that world from a yacht so big,
游艇还大到可以停直升机那种哦
you can land a helicopter on it.
我们只适合研究物理
Physics is all we're cut out for.
我们要是不当物理学家  还能当什么啊
I mean, if we weren't physicists, w-what would we be?
不知道  万人迷吧
I don't know. Popular?
没关系  我不是非要当理论物理学家
It's fine. I don't need to be a theoretical physicist.
还有很多事可以用到我的头脑
There's lots of things I could use this brain for.
我可以给黑帮当会计
I could be an accountant for the mob.
我可以在集市上猜人们的体重
I could guess people's weight at the fair.
够了  越说越蠢了
Okay. This is getting silly.
是吗
Is it?
81公斤
180.
好了
Okay.
够了
That is enough.
你们的生命没有浪费掉
Your lives are not wasted.
你们的事业没有走到死路
Your careers are not at a dead end.
你们只是遇到了一个难关
You just hit a rough patch.
不要再自怨自艾
Instead of feeling sorry for yourselves,
你们应该振作起来找灵感
you need to get up and get inspired.
怎么找
How?
我哪知道  我情绪低落的时候
I don't know. You know, when I'm feeling down,
会去跑步
I go for a run,
所以我才没有81公斤  死天才
which is exactly why I'm not 180 pounds, genius!
我知道我们该去哪里了
I know where we need to go.
是跑步去吗  因为看喝醉的谢尔顿跑步
Are we running there? Because watching drunk Sheldon run
会是我人生最值得回味的时刻
would be the highlight of my life.
我们现在去看理查德·费曼
We're going to see Richard Feynman.
佩妮  理查德·费曼是一位著名的物理...
Penny, Richard Feynman is an iconic phys...
我知道他是谁
I know who he is.
莱纳德去年万圣节扮成他
Leonard dressed as him for Halloween last year.
1988年已去世
我都不知道理查德·费曼已经去世了
I had no idea Richard Feynman was dead.
是的  但大部分人不知道
Yep. Most people don't know
他就葬在阿尔塔迪纳镇
he's actually buried right here in Altadena.
我肯定他们有意隐瞒  避免太多人来会堵车
I'm sure they keep a lid on that to avoid traffic jams.
他在这儿呢
Here he is.
他和他妻子葬在一起
Oh, wow. He's buried with his wife.
知道了  有位女士深爱过你
We get it. A lady loved you.
炫耀个屁啊
Quit bragging.
费曼真的很酷
Feynman was so cool.
我小时候会戴上耳机
When I was a kid, I'd put on some headphones
调大他讲课的音量  就这样...
and crank up one of his lectures and just...
徜徉在知识的旋律之中
jam out to knowledge.
这家伙懂得如何生活
This guy knew how to live.
他自学了各种乐器
He taught himself musical instruments.
还学会了葡萄牙语
He studied Portuguese.
就为了在巴西演讲
Just to give a speech in Brazil.
巴西式热蜡除毛通常用在女性私密部除毛
我全身只有"巴西除毛"过的部位跟巴西有关
The only part of me that's been to Brazil is my bikini line.
别再喝了
Okay.
他做了如此多壮举
He did so much.
而我们却停滞不前  令他失望
And here we are, stuck and letting him down.
费曼以前常说  他研究物理
You know, Feynman used to say he didn't do physics
不是为了名利或奖项  只是为了其中的乐趣
for the glory or the awards, but just for the fun of it.
他说得对
He was right.
只有我们不再为它兴奋激动时  物理才会死
Physics is only dead when we stop being excited about it.
即使进了坟墓  他仍在传授智慧
Even beyond the grave, he's imparting wisdom.
记得他那番话的人是我
Um, I'm the one who remembered it.
把酒给我
Give me the bottle.
可能有点俗套  但我提议
I mean, it might be a little corny, but I say
我们给所有先辈科学家
we pour one out for all the science homies
倒上一杯
who came before us.
我喜欢这提议
I love that.
要"倒"出更多酒啦
Here comes some more.
我们终于看到他醉跑了
Ah, we got to see him run.
你好  你要见我是吗
Oh, hi, you wanted to see me?
是的  我想和你谈谈
Yes. I wanted to talk to you about the e-mail
你昨晚发给我的邮件
you sent me last night.
我给你发了邮件吗
I sent you an e-mail?
确定一定以及肯定
You bet you did.
费曼是美籍犹太裔
"在此用英语  希伯来语和夏威夷语
"Hello.Shalom and aloha
从理查德·费曼的坟墓向你问好"
from the grave of Richard Feynman."
我开始想起来了
Oh, it's coming back to me.
"请接受以下撤回声明
"Please accept the following retraction:
我知道我说过物理已死
I know I said physics is dead,
其实事实恰恰相反
but it is the opposite of dead.
真要说的话
If anything,
物理是不死的  就像丧尸一样
It is undead, like a zombie.
说起这个
Speaking of which,
要是理查德·费曼变成丧尸复活
If Richard Feynman came back as a zombie,
我十分愿意让他咬我"
I would totally let him bite me."
是在这里就结束了吗
Any chance that's the end?
"我被松鼠咬过一次
"I got bit by a squirrel once.
我不得不去打狂犬病疫苗
I had to get rabies shots.
我哭得好凄惨
I cried so much,
我妈说"别哭得像个娃似地"
My mother said 'don't be a baby.'
总之
In conclusion,
物理很棒
Physics is great.
松鼠很贱  总有一天
Squirrels suck, and someday,
我要把我妈丢去便宜的养老院
I'm gonna put my mom in a cheap nursing home.
谨上
Yours, truely,
亲亲抱抱  莱纳德·霍夫斯塔德博士"
XOXO, Doctor Leonard Hofstadter."
我可以解释  我...
I can explain. I...
"附言
"PS.
你能不能来接我们
Can you come pick us up?
优步司机不肯开车门
The Uber driver won't open the door
因为谢尔顿身上沾满了蓝色呕吐物"
because Sheldon is covered in blue vomit."